<!DOCTYPE html><html lang="en"><head><meta charset="utf-8"><meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"><title>The Belltower: A weird and curious blog by Justin Taylor</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="assets/css/normalize.css"><link rel="stylesheet" href="assets/css/main.css"><link rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml" title="The Belltower: A weird and curious blog by Justin Taylor RSS" href="/rss.xml"><link href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Lato|Prata" rel="stylesheet"></head><body><main><header><h1 class="header-title">Justin Taylor</h1><nav class="main-navigation"><a href="index.html" class="navigation__link">Home</a><a href="portfolio.html" class="navigation__link">Things I've built.</a><a href="blog.html" class="navigation__link">Stuff I've written.</a><a href="contact-me.html" class="navigation__link">Get in touch.</a></nav></header><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0"><channel> <title></title><link>/<item><title>Be Persistent</title><link>/posts/hello-world<description><![CDATA[<h3>Be Persistent</h3><p>Today was my first tutorial for Microprocessors & Digital Systems. As I  worked through the exercises with minimal farting around, I noticed  something about my fellow students. Something that defined those who will probably do well over those who are gonna scrape through with a pass or less. Prior  programming experience is not the issue. Everyone here has done a  semester of python. No, the key difference is simple. It's the willingness to actually work at solving the problem in front of them, no matter what. </p><p>When my code doesn't compile, and I have no idea  why, I try a variety of things. I try a clean room rewrite of the offending function, cut it back to a working state, start over in a new file, start googling errors, sacrifice a goat to satan (hello javascript), or futzing with suspicious  code. But I don't stop trying to solve the problem. I raised my hand once to ask for help in today. I thought something was wrong with the  assessment tool. Everything looked right on my end, but the code wasn't passing assessment. By the time the tutor finished with another student  and came over, I had solved half the problem. I also knew roughly what was causing the other half. Surprise, it was a math error I'd  overlooked in my haste to try out a new feature of C I'd read about in that very tutorial. Contrast that with one of my fellow students. They raised  their hand and then talked with their friend about something meaningless until the tutor came over.</p><p>I  guess the key takeaway here is that you don't need to be smart to  succeed (god knows I'm not. I learn something new every time I do  anything, programming especially). It's as simple as being persistent.  Relentlessly, unstoppably persistent. Ask for help when you need it, but don't stop while waiting for help to arrive. </p>]]></description></item></channel></rss><hr class="overview__seperator"/><footer class="footer"><nav class="secondary-navigation"><a href="https://www.github.com/sjustintaylor" target="_blank" class="secondary-navigation__link">Github</a><a href="https://www.twitter.com/darthbobcat" target="_blank" class="secondary-navigation__link">Twitter</a></nav></footer></main><script src="assets/js/app.js"></script></body></html>